[Music]
Stanford
University all
right little a ma a mathematical
interlude we're going to be begin
with mathematical interlude is again
about linear algebra about Vector spaces
but about the idea of operators but
before we do I want to let before we get
to operators I want to say a few more
things about vectors A few more bits
about the mathematics of
vectors most of these bits have to do
not so much with deep uh mathematics as
with good notation good notation is
worth an awful lot when you can just
manipulate symbols in ways uh that are
sort of pre-arranged and uh and do it
easily and comfortably there's an
enormous benefit in that for doing
abstract mathematics certainly but also
the abstract ractions the mathematical
abstractions of
physics the abstractions that we're
going to talk about were largely due to
Der Paul dur who really was the one who
saw into the way that quantum mechanics
really fits together so let's talk about
that we have a space of states the space
of states which we'll come back to is as
I said a linear Vector space meaning to
say that you can multiply states by
numbers to get new States new ve and
these are abstract vector vectors
abstract vectors maybe I throw maybe I
throw too much in when I say the space
of States just abstract vectors you can
multiply them by numbers in our case
complex numbers and you can add them and
there are two kinds of vectors there are
the bra vectors and the C vectors
they're roughly speaking related by
complex
conjugation uh and a vector space has a
dimensionality the dimensionality is the
maximum number of orthogonal vectors
that you can find in that space and once
you know what the dimension of the space
is you can look for a basis of vectors
the basis of vectors is a mutually
orthogonal collection of normalized get
the terminology down orthonormal basis
Ortho means that they're all orthogonal
to each other normal the word normal
means normalized and normalized simply
means that the vectors are of unit
length
a collection of them that is maximal in
other words that you can't find anymore
because there are no more directions
left that defines a basis and the number
of them is equal to the uh the
dimensionality of the space given such a
basis you can make you can write any
Vector in the space as some kind of sum
over those basis vectors so we can write
for any Vector
a that it's equal to sum sum over I I
here stands for the basis vectors oh of
course a basis is not a unique thing
just as there are many sets of mutually
orthogonal vectors in three-dimensional
space there are many sets of mutually
orthogonal
vectors in uh in an abstract Vector
space but we pick one we pick a set
having picked that set and we label it I
we can write any Vector as a sum Alpha
sub I exactly those Alphas which uh
which we refer to a moment ago Alpha
subi a set of complex numbers a set of
complex coefficients times the I basis
Vector the I basis Vector
uh
uh I'm labeling I this is a k
representation but now what we can do
with this is we can take the inner
product with it I want to try to
calculate these Alpha subis in terms of
some Quant quantities involving the
vectors themselves all right so what we
do is we take the inner product of both
sides of the equation with the basis
Vector J the K Vector J on the left hand
side we get the inner product of the
vector a which is the thing
we're trying to express and that's equal
to the sum of a i Alpha sub I times the
inner product of the vector J with the
vector I
but the inner product of the vector J
with this Vector I is either one or zero
it's one if I and J are the same vector
and it's zero otherwise why because
they're orthogonal if I is not equal to
J and then normalized namely of unit
length if I does equal J so this bracket
over here this product of bras and KS is
just the chronic symbol Delta Del j k
Sorry Delta
ji0 or one and when you do the sum it
just picks out one and only one
contribution the contribution in which I
is equal to J so on the right hand side
you just get Alpha J no sum the sum has
collapsed to one term and that's now
equal to J A all right so what have we
learned we've learned that the
coefficient here in the expansion of any
Vector is just the inner product
of the J Vector with the target Vector
with the the vector we're trying to
describe
uh the fact that I wrote A J there is
irrelevant it could also be Alpha I
doesn't matter which I or which J
the I coefficient is in in a product
now I can use that to rewrite the sum up
here I now know what the alpha subis are
they're these guys over here so let's
rewrite this sum over I I'm going to
start with Alpha I oh sorry with I and
then write Alpha subi I'm going to write
Alpha subi next to it over here in the
opposite order that that's that's
allowed nothing uh nothing
non-commutative at this stage now now I
want to write Alpha sub I so I write
I
a that's a basic
formula that any Vector can be Rewritten
in terms of
its coefficients or in terms of its
inner product with the basis
vectors times the basis vectors
themselves Su over I it's kind of a
pretty
formula and it comes back over and over
again what it says is whenever you see
this summation of I * I in that form you
can sort of throw it away it's just a
equals a
but it's an expression for a vector in
terms of its
components all right so that's uh one
simple fact the same thing is true for
bra
vectors exactly the same thing is true
for bra vectors and you would write it
in the following form
a bra
Vector is also a sum of I
of the inner product of the bra bra
Vector with the basis vectors times the
basis bra vectors the basis bra vectors
are just the complex conjugates if you
like of the basic the basis K vectors
both of these equations are true and
we're going to find out that they're
enormously useful
they're enormously
useful and Powerful even though they
were very very
simple all right now we come to the
notion of linear
operators States in quantum mechanics
are
vectors and we saw a little bit about
how that
works in the case of a single spin
observables observables mean the things
that we
measure the things that we measure the
objects that we measure the quantities
that we measure the observables are
related to linear operators in the space
all right so what is a linear
operator and it'll take us the rest of
the evening to understand in any detail
what it has to do with
observables so put that out of your head
for the moment we're just doing a
mathematical interlude now what is the
notion of a linear
operator a linear
operator is is
a process if you like which you apply to
vectors somebody or other I can't
remember who it might have been John
Wheeler like to describe these things as
machines he would say a linear operator
is a machine with two um little ports in
it into one port you put an input vector
and then you turn the wheel and out
comes an output vector so it's an in
it's a thing which acts on an input
Vector to give an output
Vector so let's uh let's call m a linear
operator linear is linear will come to
so far we're just talking about operator
a machine in goes one end out comes
another end and we'll talk about what it
means for it to be linear linear in a
minute all right so m is some operator
and that means
that given any
Vector when M acts on it it simply gives
another
Vector
unique given any a it gives a unique
B that does not mean the converse may
not be Converse opposite I don't know
may not be true it may not be
uh that given a B on this side that
there's only one unique a that gives
rise to that b but it is true that M
applied to any Vector a gives a unique
reflection of
a which is the process M acting on a now
what does it mean for M to be a linear
operator well first of
all M can act on Z * a where Z * a is a
vector in fact let's write the let's
write that uh yeah M can act on Z * a z
* a is itself a vector because you're
allowed to multiply vectors by complex
numbers Z is a complex number the rule
about linear operators is if they apply
on constants times Vector they just give
back the constant times what they would
have given on
a all right so it just means that a z a
complex number
a complex number can be brought through
m m acting on twice a gives twice what M
would have given on a m acting on 3 * a
gives three times what M gives on a m
acting on I times a the complex number
of I just gives I times whatever M would
give on a that's the first rule about
linearity and the second rule about
linearity is that if M acts on the sum
of two
vectors
A+
B then what you get is just the sum of
what the machine spit out for a and what
the machine spit out for B what the
machine spits out when you put in a plus
b is just the sum of what comes
out
M *
A+ m
times B and that's it that's that's the
notion of a linear operator there's no
more to it than
that
uh or at least that's the full set of uh
rules about linear
operators now let's see if we can be
more concrete about
them and see if we can learn to
manipulate with them let's suppose
that M * a equals
B here I've used b as a as a piece of
the input but now B is the output A and
B are just letters I can use them any
way I want M * aals
B I'm
interested in the component of b along
the axis I by that I mean these objects
over here the alphas they are the
components of the vector a along the
various basis Vector
directions so Alpha subis are the
components of the vectors and I'm
interested in the components of the
output Vector I would like to know in a
concrete way what are the components of
B so to find out I just project them
onto the direction
i a
m i all I've done is in both sides of
the equation project or to project this
does take the inner product with the
vector I this by
definition is beta
I in other words if I were to expand B
in the same way I expanded a I would use
the coefficients beta I that's what we
learned up on the top board this is beta
I how about over here what can I do with
this to rewrite things in terms of
components I want to rewrite everything
in terms of components so they actually
become arithmetical operations that you
can do well here's where we use this
trick that whenever you see a vector a
you can substitute for
it a
[Music]
sum let's do that right in here where a
is let's substitute
I I have haven't substituted yet
now the summation variable is not I in
this case I I've used as the external
non-s summation variable here so let's
sum over J doesn't matter what we call a
summation variable J
A I've stuck in for a the sum of the
components times the J Vector times a
j basis Vector but now a * J go up to
the top
again that's just Alpha
J so we now have a formula completely in
terms of
components this is i m j I'll get to
this in a minute but it's a number inner
products are numbers M * J is a vector
and you can take its inner product with
I right M * J is a vector
and vectors K vectors have inner
products with basis vectors
times J A or times Alpha
J that's equal to Beta
I so all we have to do is give this
object a
name what is this object just I tell you
again you have some operator it's an
abstract entity you have a collection of
basis vectors you apply the abstract
operator to the vector J and take its
inner product with I and call the thing
m j it's a number it may be a complex
number but it's a
number in other words it's possible to
characterize linear
operators
by what I call their Matrix elements
these are called The Matrix elements of
the linear
operator M this times Alpha J summed
over J I left I left out the sum over J
here let's put it back in sum on J is
equal to Beta
I if somebody hands you the collection
of
MJS and somebody hands you a vector in
the form of its
components you can then start sweeping
through it and calculating what the
components of the output are in terms of
the
input m j is a matrix it has two indices
it's a square Matrix if the
dimensionality of the space is n then m
is an n m is an N byn Matrix a square
matrix it's a square Matrix Alpha can be
regarded Ed as a
column Alpha can be regarded as a column
and the output is also a
column it's a column because a was a k
vector and B was a c Vector all right so
another way to write the same thing this
is one way to write M * AAL B well
here's one way to write it abstract
here's another way to write it as a
concrete sum and the Third Way is to
recognize that this is just the
multiplication of a matrix times a
column
Vector you write the Matrix
M by displaying all of its
components
M11 M12 M13 dot dot dot M21 M22 dot dot
dot dot dot dot dot
dot it's just an array that exhibits The
Matrix elements we now learn to call
these The Matrix elements of M
times the column Vector a alpha 1 Alpha
2 dot dot dot alpha
n and what is the rule this this of
course is supposed to result in an
output which is beta 1 beta 2 dot dot
beta
n all right what's the rule that's
implied by this equation over here it's
very simple if you want the first entry
over here
you take the first row and you take its
inner product with a column here m not
the inner well you can call it the inner
product M11 alpha 1 plus M12 Alpha 2
plus M13 Alpha 3 right down to the
bottom that's exactly
this formula
M12 sorry M11 alpha 1 plus M12 Alpha 2
and so forth is exactly the standard
rule for multiplying a matrix by a
column
Vector all right so now we have a third
way to represent the action of a matrix
on a
vector this is less
abstract it's concrete if you know the
Matrix elements you know exactly what to
do with them the only thing about it is
it does depend on a particular choice of
your basis
vectors the specifics of the Matrix
element here and the column Vector will
depend on your choice of once you pick a
a basis you stick with
it but you could have chosen a different
basis in which case these components
would have been different The Matrix
elements would have been different after
all the Matrix elements are themselves
related to the basis vectors and so you
lose something and you gain something by
going to a matrix type representation
what you lose is
the geometric idea of a relationship
between two vectors that's independent
of the basis
Choice what you gain is a computational
actual mechanical algorithm for
producing or for the machine itself here
is the machine the machine is a matrix
and what it does is it grinds through
M11 alpha 1 blah blah blah blah blah
then it goes to the next row does the
thing again goes to the next row does
the thing again and just spits out the
final
answer these things are of course also
true for ordinary vectors in
three-dimensional space they're not the
specific uh we tend not to use them as
much in three-dimensional ordinary
vectors but they're quite um essential
to in quantum mechanics yes this may be
getting ahead um could the choice basis
factors ever make a difference to
whether or not you can see the solution
to a problem
well all right the precise way you ask
it whether it can make a difference to
the way you see through a problem
certainly a wrong choice of basis can
leave you uh completely confused I think
what you really meant is can can
different choices or bases lead to
different physical answers and that had
better not be then you're doing
something
wrong yeah yeah it's often the case that
that a convenient choice of basis will
make your computations especially
simple uh and a bad choice of basis
might make them horribly complicated
that's true but uh but at the end of the
day the answers should not depend on it
the result of an
experiment okay so now we have we have
the idea of a linear
operator operating on a and several
different uh versions of it
question yeah is it
legitimate it seems that within a
definition linear operator you have an
operator that gives you a cat Vector
from a bra Vector Vice ver no no no no
no no no no no linear operators act on K
vectors to give K vectors
complexation that's right complex ah
very good all right let's yeah um the
simplest kind of uh of
linear operator is just multiplication
by a complex number I just multiply a by
a complex number and get uh get another
Vector it's basically the same Vector
but uh twice as long or something that
is a linear
operator you might ask whether complex
conjugation is a linear
operator I take I take the components of
a vector and replace them by their
complex conjugates the answer is no it
is not
uh and you can check the definitions
multiplying the components of the vector
or not multiplying them by complex
conjugating them is not what it does do
is it takes a
vector and it's a different kind of
machine complex conjugation it's a
machine which takes a bra Vector to a k
vector or a k Vector to a bra vector and
that's a that's strictly it's called an
anti-linear
operator uh it's not anti-linear I mean
it's just it's it's not the opposite of
linear it's just a
word well the reason it's a word the
reason it was called an anti-linear is
because the process of complex
conjugation is in some deep way related
to anti particles but uh we're not there
yet
um
yeah all right now let's talk let's talk
about K ve uh sorry bra
vectors so far we have defined our
linear
operators to act only on K
vectors but every linear operator can
also be given a definition we need a
definition of course we haven't defined
it yet we need a definition but there is
also a definition of Any Given linear
operator acting on a bra Vector okay
let's see if we can
uh concoct a definition and then we'll
stick with that
definition
what might be the
rules for the action of that same linear
operator when it acts on a bra Vector
first of all the standard notation and
it's very very good to keep track of
notation and to use the same notation
over it's not only neat but it keeps uh
keeps things uh in
order when you act on a bra Vector put
the corresponding operator on the right
right side of it all right it gives
something take that something and take
its inner product let's put a bracket
around it to
indicate that M acting on a is itself an
entity and now let's take its in a
product with another
Vector
B well if I removed the bracket here I
would have a
which would look like this a m b and I
really wouldn't know if what I'm
supposed to do is act with M on B and
then take the inner product with a or
act with M on a and then take the inner
product with
B the answer is with the standard
definition of how linear operators act
to the left on bra vectors it doesn't
matter in other words we Define the
action of an m on an a to the left such
that and I'll show you that we can
always do this such that it doesn't
matter which way we do
it okay a MB is the same as a m
b uh that you can remove the
brackets
okay let's see that we can do this in
order to see it let's start with the
definition this
way let's start with a definition this
way where's my I don't ah okay start
with a definition this way and now I'm
going to use that trick up on the top
where you write a vector by inserting
this there's a name for this operation
here it's called inserting a complete
set of states
complete simply means it's a
basis it's called inserting a complete
set of states it did nothing it took a
and it rewrote a but it rewrote a in
terms of its components so let's do that
over on B over here we can do the same
thing over here we can write that this
is equal to
B
J J summed over J I'm not going to write
the summation signs maybe I'll put them
I'll put them at the end out here
summation I and
J all right so this is the same Vector
as
B then put M there let's put the bracket
around it put M there and now do exactly
the same thing on the K Vector remember
the K Vector can also be expanded in the
same way so here we go
a
i i
what do we see here we
see this is Alpha star I why did I put
the I why did I put the star
there because the bra vectors are
complex conjugates there's Alpha I
there's an m
j i in a product of i m * J and then
there is B
J that's all we have here this is summed
on I and
J M with I on the left and J on the
right that's m j j beta Alpha
I and you can see from the way that
we've written this that it doesn't
matter if I first sum over J and think
of M as acting on on on the K Vector
beta or I sum over I
and think of M as first acting to the
left on Alpha you get the same answer
it's just a double sum over I and J you
get the same answer and so if
you
define you in other words you can would
not you can Define m in such a way that
it doesn't matter which order not which
order or way you put the
brackets that eases your life you don't
have to remember whether you meant MX on
B and then you take the inner product
with a or MX on a and then you take the
inner product with B same
thing okay but there is a there
is
that's it's a power of a nice
notation but now let's consider another
question
supposing that the linear operator M on
a gives B
incidentally I'm using A and B all over
the place in different
ways there it was just two vectors here
a is the input Vector B is the output
Vector so let's suppose that the machine
M when you stick a into it outs spits
B we could ask what's the
corresponding uh bra Vector relationship
is there a linear operator which has the
property that when it acts
on I'm not going to call it m yet it's
not M let's call it scripty
m is there for every M which acts on a
to give B is there a corresponding scrip
the M which acts on the corresponding
bra
vector
B to give the corresponding bra Vector
over here well yes there is and we're
going to figure out how to figure out
what it is soon enough but it is not the
original m one example would be what if
M was just multiplication by a complex
number then what would script the M
be multiplication by the complex
conjugate number
so whatever m is it's not necessarily
the same as script the M it would be the
same as script the M if it was comp if
it was multiplication by a real number
but if it's multiplication by a complex
number then in general well in general
it will not give uh the same
relationship we would normally just put
a complex conjugate sign if we want it
to operate on the in the other direction
all right the notation that is standard
is to say that the operator which went
acting to the
left is the reflection if you like is
the Duel of the oper of the op operator
M acting to the right that is not called
M it is called
M
dagger the
dagger is a m is a operative version of
complex
conjugation it's an operative
version of complex conjugation or Matrix
version of complex conjugation it's
called hermiss conjugation but we uh
we'll get to these fancy words soon
enough well okay this is abstract but
let's see if we can get to a
concrete
notion MJ the abstract operator is
equivalent to a concrete Matrix if I
give you the concrete Matrix then I'm
giving you m the question is in terms of
that concrete Matrix is there a concrete
Matrix for M dagger and the answer is
yes how do we find it we find it just by
proceeding Dead
Ahead I would like to know
what the
uh The Matrix elements let's see which
way I did
it yeah
yeah this is what I would call the IJ
Matrix element of M dagger I don't know
what M dagger is yet I have a suspicion
that's something to do with complex
conjugates but this is its Matrix
elements concrete set of
numbers uh can we find out what they are
all right uh yeah I think we have to
step back for a minute let me suppose
that M acts on the basis Vector to give
I
prime I prime is just the result of
sticking the basis Vector into the
machine into the M machine and this is
what comes out let's suppose that's the
result okay now let's
take j m
i that's equal to j i Prime
all I've done is take the inner product
with
J here's the Matrix element of the
Matrix M and it's just this inner
product it's that was a trivial
operation I didn't do anything okay I
didn't do anything very
significant if this is true then by
definition then by
definition M dagger
acting to the left what does m dagger
acting to the left give on
I okay look at this equation here M
dagger when it acts to the
left gives the bra Vector
B right so that's what all that dagger
does is it sort of turns the equation
over so what does m dagger acting on I
give it gives the bra Vector I
prime if M dagger on the bra I it must
give the bra Vector I prime it just
flips the equation from bras to cats so
what we have over here then is I prime
J that's the Matrix element that's this
Matrix element over
here okay so let's look what we have we
have the Matrix element of M is the
inner product of J with I
Prime The Matrix element of M dagger is
the inner product of I Prime with J
what's the relationship between these
two
transpose transposing complex conjugate
just a complex
conjugate if you take two vectors A and
B and you think of them in the opposite
order the bra a time a k b versus the
bra B * the k a the relationship between
them is just complex
conjugation so this here is just the
complex conjugate of
this so what we've
derived is that the Matrix element the
IJ Matrix element of M dagger is the
complex
conjugate of the J
he Matrix element of
M so if I know the Matrix elements of
M what do I do to get the Matrix
elements of M dagger it's very simple
you complex conjugate but that's not
quite enough you complex conjugate and
you
interchange I's and J's
you interchange I and
J okay another way to write it is that M
dagger i j is equal to
mji
Star so now we know a lot we know we
know how to
construct operators which act to the
left to do the same mapping that they
did when they went to the the right they
map the bra a to the bra B if the
original operator did the same thing on
the
cats all right that's the notion of
hermiss conjugation this is called
hermiss conjugation the word
[Music]
hermiss is named after some
mathematician whose name was
hermite and her Mission uh conjugation
is the process of interchanging I and J
and taking its complex conjugate in
terms of
matrices if I have a
matrix this is an easy way to remember
it M11 M12 dot dot dot M21
M22 if that's the
Matrix representing M then the Matrix
representing its conjugate its Herm
mission conjugate is to Simply
interchange rows and
columns that means reflecting it about
the
diagonal and then complex
conjugating interchanging I and
J that's like interchanging M12 with
M21 you just flip it about the diagonal
and you complex conjugate
it so if I want the Matrix elements of
the Herm mission
conjugate well I I can't say it anymore
just just do what I said you interchange
rows and columns and you complex
conjugate interchanging rows and columns
is the same thing as reflecting about
the the
diagonal right you reflect about the
diagonal let's do it and then you
complex
conjugate Let me Give an example
supposing I have the
Matrix two
6 + I uh 6 + I * 7 4 - I and N 9 plus I
okay 9 plus I what's the hermiss
conjugate of that all right you first
flip it flipping it leaves the diagonal
elements in place and interchanges the
off diagonal
elements so you flip it 2 9 +
I 6 +
uh I *
7 4 -
I what is that process called of
flipping it like that transpose that's
called a transpose so flipping is a
transpose but then you have to complex
conjugate it complex conjugating just
means wherever you see I put minus I so
this becomes 4 + I 1 - 7 I and 9 - I and
that's the The Matrix that represents
the hermiss conjugate of the original
Matrix so it's easy this it's uh it's
easy it's concrete and it's also
abstract it has an abstract side the
hermiss conjugate just allows you to
turn an equation from a braet a bra
Vector to a c vector and in terms of
concrete Matrix elements you flip I and
J and you complex conjugate and that
defines M
Daga
now as I said in general these matrices
are thought of as complex
objects and the notion of complex
conjugation is replaced by this hermiss
conjugation simultaneous flipping and uh
right now what is a real number a real
number is one which is its own complex
conjugate if I write that Z is equal to
Z Star you jump up and you say that is a
real
number there's a corresponding notion
for
operators it's the notion of an
operator which is its own Herm Mission
conjugate an operator which is its own
Herm Mission
conjugate that means you interchange and
complex conjugate and you get back to
the same thing that is called Herm
Mission Herm mission is the analog for
matrices or the analog for operators of
real all right so what it says a Herm
Mission Matrix now let's specialize to
the case of Herm Mission
matrices and just spell out her mission
for
you
permission for matrices is the analog of
real for numbers a Herm
Mission operator or Matrix is one which
is equal to its own Herm Mission
conjugate in terms of
matrices it's m
j is equal to
mji
Star let's try to see if we can
construct a Herm Mission Matrix in uh
yeah let's see if we can construct a
Herm Mission Matrix
the first thing about Herm Mission
matrices is their diagonal elements are
always real take a diagonal element for
a diagonal element I and J are equal i j
is the same as j i if on the diagonal so
that says that for the diagonal elements
they're always real so Herm Mission
Matrix first of all has real diagonal
elements uh 1 7 I don't know I like
s uh minus
2.6 on the
diagonal off the diagonal they have the
property that when you reflect them they
simply complex conjugate so if we were
to put I over here we would put minus I
over here for a Herm Mission Matrix if
you were to
put 4 minus I over here you would put
four plus I over here and if you had
five over here you'd put five over here
all right so Herm Mission Matrix has the
property first of all diagonal elements
are real and the off diagonal elements
not
symmetric but a different kind of
symmetry a symmetry where when you
reflect them they complex conjugate
that's called a Herm Mission Matrix a
Herm Mission Matrix has an enormous
importance in uh hermiss matrices have
enormous importance in quantum mechanics
they represent the observable quantities
the measurable quantities the things
that you can
measure we're going to come to that and
we're going to do a bit of that
especially for the single spin I hope
tonight but before we do we have to know
a little more about Herm Mission
matrices in particular we need a concept
the concept of igen vector and igen
value right now I know that I'm going
fast and I know I'm quite aware that if
you don't know these ideas is you're
going to have to uh uh struggle tonight
to keep up but there there standard
ideas there are lots of textbooks on
linear algebra you can find it and you
can sit down quietly and uh and learn
these ideas in about two hours I would
say two three
hours okay
so let's talk about her Mission well
let's first talk about igen vectors and
igen
values
we can even think about these things
incidentally in ordinary
three-dimensional space where the vector
space is just the space of ordinary
three
vectors uh there are operators they're
represented by matrices and those
operators operate on vectors to give
other vectors and typically if a matrix
is at all interesting or if an operator
is at all interesting whatever it mean
to be interesting well if it's at all a
little bit complex it will generally
have the property that if you put a
vector into the machine the vector that
comes out will be pointing in a
different direction that will be
generally true generically
true uh so directionality is not
preserved by linear operators as a rule
on the other hand there may be
particular vectors and typically there
are particular
vectors uh that uh when you apply a
matrix those vectors will depend on
which Matrix you're talking about or an
operator there may be specific vectors
associated with a specific operator that
do simply get multiplied by numbers in
other words they come out in the same
direction an
example uh an example of a operation a
linear operation on a vector is a
rotation about an axis that can be
represented by a
matrix um in three dimensions if you
rotate the vector space about some axis
then generally speaking an arbitrary
Vector will wind up in a different
direction however there is one
particular direction for which that
doesn't happen namely along the axis of
rotation if you rotate about the axis of
rotation the vector comes out pointing
in the same direction it comes out of
multiple of itself now in this case
simply equal to
itself all right so that's the that's
the notion of the igen vectors of an
operator they are the
vectors if there are any they're not
necessarily
any for example in rotations about two
and two Dimensions there are no igen
vectors there are no directions which
come out in no directions which come out
unaffected
but so in general it may or may not be
uh uh igen vectors but if there are igen
vectors they're defined in the following
way again I'm going to use M for the
generic
operator M acts on an igen Vector let's
call the Igan Vector
I I for igen now of course I is not for
igen igen begins with an
e but I'm going to call it I anyway all
right if n
acts on one of its igen vectors igen
vectors are not things which are
independent of the matrices given a mat
a matrix or an operator it has certain
igen directions or certain igen
vectors and the rule is or the
definition is the set of vectors which
just get multiplied by
numbers let's call for the I igen Vector
here the igen value is called Lambda I
and it simply multiplies the
input now different igen
vectors of the same Matrix will have
different igen values there may be and
in general that's that's the generic
situation if there are several igen ve
vectors they will have different igen
values however the igen vectors are not
completely
unambiguous if you take an igen vector
and multiply it by a number the result
is still an igen Vector with the same
igen
value If I multiply this equation by a
complex number Z I can bring the complex
number Z through and I'll find out that
any numerical even complex numerical
multiple of an igen Vector is also an
igen
Vector
uh so strictly speaking you should talk
about igen directions the set of vectors
uh is uh uh including
or not worrying about their length so to
speak but in any case this is the
direction of an this is the definition
of an igen
Vector all right some matrices have igen
vectors other matrices don't have igen
vectors there is something important
about Herm Mission matrices or Herm
Mission operators Herm Mission operators
not only have igen
vectors they have a complete set of igen
vectors complete means that there are
enough of them to expand any vector and
even
better they have an orthonormal family
of igen
vectors in general the different igen
vectors will have different igen values
as I said but it will be true that if a
matrix is Herm
Mission it has and the dimensionality of
the spaces in there will be in mutually
orthog igen
vectors in other words the igen vectors
of Herm Mission matrices Define a
basis I'm going to let you Pro prove
part of that theorem it's a very easy
theorem to prove and I'm going to prove
the other half of it I'll prove the half
that says that if you have two igen
vectors with different igen values and
that's the generic situation that the
igen values are all different if you
have two igen vectors with different
igen values we will prove that they're
orthogonal to each
other your job is to prove that you
won't run out of igen vectors until you
have n of
them it's not hard it's not hard in any
case it's true all right so let's prove
that if we have two IG vectors let's m
is a Herm Mission all right let's m is
Herm
Mission m equals a Herm Mission
Matrix I use Matrix and operator
synonymously which means that m equals m
Daga okay let's suppose that m is
hermiss and it has an igen value Lambda
I the first observation is that the igen
values of Herm Mission matrices are real
that that even comes before what I said
previously if there is an igen value it
is real okay how do we prove that it's
real let's let's prove that it's real
well let's take this equation and flip
it over into a bra equation to flip it
over into a bra
equation I flip
I I take M and I replace it by m
dagger well that's not going to do much
because m is equal to M
dagger and on the right hand side I flip
I and what do I do with
Lambda in
general complex
conjugate complex conjugate Lambda R so
far we haven't proved that it's
real right every time you flip uh from
bras to cats you have to complex
conjugate all the numbers that are there
all right but now assumption m is Herm
Mission so it's equal to its own
om Mission
conjugate and now we have this
equation now let's take the inner
product of both of these equations with
I and the upper equation we're going to
take the inner
product on the left with I and what does
that give us that gives us I I time
Lambda I
let's do the same thing over
here except
now multiplying on the
right this and this are obviously the
same M with I on the left and I on the
right is the same as
this but this is not obviously the same
not unless Lambda is equal to Lambda the
star II here is the same as I I here
that cancels out and therefore we come
to the conclusion that if a matrix is
Herm
Mission if it's equal to its own Herm
Mission conjugate then its igen values
are equal to their own complex
conjugates and they are real igen values
are permission matrices are real that's
the first
step now let's prove that if we have two
different igen values the corresponding
igen vectors must be orthogonal now
remember what orthogonal means from a
physical point of view it means
physically distinct that there's an
experiment that you can do to
distinguish the two of them
unambiguously that's what orthogonality
means from a physical point of view
let's prove that the igen vectors of M
with different igen value are
orthogonal different Dion value
physically distinguishable you should
keep that in your head okay so here we
are let's let's start with M on
I equal Lambda i
i and m on
J equals Lambda J J two different D
vectors I and
J first thing we'll do is turn this one
over and turn it into a k equation ah a
bra it is equation we'll take this one
and turn it into a bra equation so that
looks like this
J M dagger but M dagger is the same as
m equals the real number Lambda J igen
Vector igen values of permission
matrices are real times
J now here we have okay so we we have
two equations
what can you do to them so that we can
relate them what we can do with them to
relate them is to multiply this one by J
on the left and this one by I on the
right and we will get the same
expression on the left hand side of the
equation so let's do that
j
i i
what we have on the left is the same on
the upper and lower equation what we
have on the right is not necessarily the
same so let's require that it's the same
requiring that it's the same says that
Lambda I minus Lambda
J times the inner product of J with
I must equal Z I've I've just written a
fanc I've just written that this is
equal to this and then
transposed all right so Lambda IUS
Lambda J * the inner product of j i
equals
z well if the product of two things and
I have two things Lambda I minus Lambda
J and the inner product of J with J If
the product of two things is zero it
says
unambiguously at least one of them is
zero
it usually says one of them is zero okay
the inner product of I and J may or may
not be zero but let's take the case
where we know that the igen vectors
correspond to different values of the
igen ve sorry that the igen values are
different that's what I'm interested in
I'm interested in igen vectors
corresponding to different values of the
igen value so by assumption Lambda I is
not equal to Lambda J the conclusion is
that the inner product of I with J must
be equal to zero so what does that mean
that means that I and J are orthogonal
so we now have a
theorem the igen
vectors of Herm Mission matrices with
different igen value are
orthogonal uh let's uh just take the
generic case where all of the igen
values are different we can come back to
what happens when some of them may be
the same that's not not not important
right now if all the igen values have to
be happen to be different than each
other then all the igen vectors are
mutually orthogonal to each
other if there are enough of them and
your job is to prod prove there's enough
of them they form a basis in other words
this collection of things called I and J
here is a special case of the kind of
basis which we labeled with small inj
but it's the Bas basis of igen
vectors it's the basis of igen vectors
of the Herm Mission
operator as I said Herm Mission
operators will be identified with
observable
quantities and to say that igen vectors
are orthogonal has something or other to
do with physical differences that are
measurable unambiguously between those
uh those states of the
system okay we are now prepared to state
the principles of quantum
mechanics we have enough
mathematical information or enough
mathematical
formalism to
State the entire show we can put on the
Blackboard now what quantum mechanics is
and what it says and uh what the rules
are or what the correspondences
are what the mathematical sorry what the
um what the physical meaning of these
various things
are you won't get the you won't
understand this the first time around
it'll be foreign it'll be peculiar what
is he talking about but of course we'll
work it out in examples and we'll see
how the ideas work so don't get
Disturbed if what I throw at you now uh
sounds a little bit
meaningless that's okay by the time
we're finished with some examples it
should be clear how we use this
all right first of all there are
measurable quantities the result of a
measurement is always a real
number it takes at least two
measurements and two somehow two
compatible measurements two measurements
that can both be performed
simultaneously to measure a complex
number right the basic ingredients and
basic measurables are real numbers
that's what comes out of your detector
you can measure two of them if you can
measure two of them if it's possible to
simultaneously measure two things and
put them together into a complex number
but it really is just two measurements
so each measurement each thing that you
measure has a real result associated
with
it the physical measurables they're
called observables in quantum mechanics
they're called observables the things
that you can measure the
observables are identified with Herm
Mission matrices or Herm Mission
operators
observables whoops not Q where did I get
Q
from I won't write equals are
represented by we'll just put an arrow
are represented by Herm
Mission linear of course
operators
first
statement let's just think in studying
the spin in a uh in a uh in a in a rough
and loose way we sort of identified some
observables the observables that we
identified were the components of the
spin the observables that we could
identify or associated with our
apparatus Point your apparatus in some
direction and measure the spin along
those directions we said we called if we
measured the spin along the z-axis we
called it Sigma Z we can measure
it or we could turn our apparatus on its
side and measure Sigma
X or we can turn apparatus
um uh from the x- axis to the Y AIS and
measure Sigma y we talked about uh those
things we didn't talk about sigmas being
Herm Mission operators
in fact we didn't talk about them being
operators at all but we did talk about
measuring them these will become Herm
Mission operators in time okay all right
next the possible values that a given
observable can take on what are they for
Sigma
Z what are the
possible plus one or minus one right
okay the possible observable
values
measured in an
experiment those observable values are
the igen
values they're real because the matrices
are Herm
Mission the igen vectors what about the
igen vectors the igen vectors correspond
to States states vectors States vectors
the igen
vectors are the states in which the
corresponding quantities are definite in
other words in which the measurement of
them is unambiguous oh well let's let's
uh yeah let's uh let's follow through on
this here a little bit for all three of
these observables the igen values had
better be plus or minus
one okay now let's come to the igen
vectors the igen vectors
for example the igen vector with a given
igen value is a state of the system
where if you measure that particular
observable you will definitely get the
igen value associated with that igen
Vector so the igen
vectors those
are I think I have it backwards we
should put igen vectors on this side
and on the left side the physical
meaning of them the physical
meaning is
States in
which
observable has
unambiguous
unambiguous result
example we talked for example about the
states up and
down those are states in which Sigma Z
had definite values when you're up Sigma
Z is definitely one when you're down
Sigma Z is definitely minus one any
other Vector Sigma Z is statistically uh
uh either plus or minus one but with a
Randomness okay so up and down must be
the igen vectors of Sigma
Z left and right were the states in
which Sigma X was unambiguously either
plus one or minus one so left and right
must be the igen vectors of Sigma X
whatever Sigma X is we're going to try
to figure out what Sigma X is knowing
its igen values knowing it igen values
and its igen vector
s and what was the other three the other
two called in and out I think yeah in
and out were the igen vectors of Sigma
y so we have three connections and now a
fourth
connection given a general State not an
igen Vector not an igen
vector
given a general State
a somebody made an electron or a system
of some sort and left it in the state a
then we can talk about what is the
probability that we measure the igen
values of
M at different values there may be
several different igen values in this
case they would be plus one and minus
one but more generally thousand igen
values a million igen values whatever
whatever the number is labeled by the uh
the label I what is the probability that
when you measure M you get Lambda
I that's the last piece of uh thing here
so on the left hand side we put
probability physical meaning
probability and I'll write it just as
the probability to measure I no to
measure Lambda I I'm sorry to measure
Lambda
I that the result of the experiment
comes out a particular igen value of the
observable m whatever m
is
that is related not related to it's
essentially equal to well two pieces
comes in two steps first you calculate
if you have the the the vector a the
vector which you start that's the state
of the system you take its inner
product with the igen vector
I the projection of a onto I the
component of a in the I Direction now
that in general is a complex number that
is not the probability you multiply it
by its own complex conjugate to get a
real positive number and that is the
probability
we can multiply this by its complex
conjugate or we can just write it I a
this I a and AI are complex conjugates
of each other we can also write this as
the absolute value of I a
squared the individual components before
we Square them are called amplitudes
they're called probability
amplitudes probability amplitudes are
things which you multiply by their
complex conjugates to find probabilities
they're real they're
positive and that's the
fourth the fourth
postulate of quantum mechanics now
they're not all independent uh I use
them because uh because they're
reasonably intuitive in fact you can
probably get rid of at least two of them
and prove them from the other from the
others but we don't need to do that
this is a good starting point
um and these are the basic four
postulates of quantum mechanics okay the
other postulate is that when you measure
a quantity you prepare the system in a
state of definite value of that quantity
I won't bother writing that down when
you measure something you are in effect
pushing it into a state of definite
value of that quantity depending on what
the outcome of your experiment is if
your outcome measures some particular if
the outcome of an experiment is some
particular igen value that means you
pushed the system into the state into
the igen state of that quantity with
that IG value I won't write that down it
takes too many words to write it
down it's under the P the the
probability
I yeah uh next to the P what is that I
can't with your handwriting p
o p o b Pro it's probably probable
probably
probability
yeah this reads the probability of
measuring Lambda oh it is Lambda I
Lambda I the probability of measuring
Lambda I is the square of the inner
product of a with I
it's if you like it's the
projection of a onto the I direction or
the component of a in the I Direction
now there's an implication here there's
an implication here about the nature of
State
vectors coming from the assumption that
total probabilities are equal to one be
normalized what that I just said they
have to be normalized yeah yeah let's uh
let's work that out
if you want the total probability to add
up to
one then you
want the sums of all these objects when
you sum over I over the various possible
values
of that you can measure you want that to
equal one so you want the sum of I for
any
allowable State
a we want the sum of
a
i
a to equal
one now I is a basis and if you go up to
the top equation there you have
equations which tell you how to deal
with exactly this combination
what is the sum of a i of i i
a it's just a so what this says is that
the inner product of a with itself
should equal one the total length of a
should be equal to one that's not too
surprising that that's what this says
this says the sums of the squares of the
components of a add up to
one for ordinary vectors that would just
say the length of the vector was one and
that's what this says the length of a is
equal to 1
it's equivalent in terms of the alphas
we got rid yeah the alphas are up there
also it's equivalent to the sum of alpha
star I Alpha I equals
1 well I capital
I and so there is
one combination of the alphas this is
one real equation it's not a complex
equation it's a real equation and that
means there's one real combination of
the alphas which has to be
constrained Alphas are not completely
free or the alphas are not completely
free the roughly speaking the sums of
their squares or the sums of them times
a complex conjugate has to add up to one
so that means there's less uh fewer
independent quantities than you
thought there is another fact which we
have not gotten to yet we will get to
it um you can sort of see it from
here all probabilities any probability
that you ever may want to measure or
that you ever may want to uh uh to
calculate or compare with experiment is
always connected with a real quantity
like
this the collection of such real
quantities uh is invar under a certain
operation the operation is multiplying
the state vector by a phase everybody
know what it means to multiply a number
a thing by a
phase you multiply it by an e to the I
Theta if you multiply all the components
of
a by the same overall phase then every
probability is
unchanged every probability is
unchanged uh
even if you rotate bases it's unchanged
So Physical quantities don't respond to
a change of the
phase that means there are two
fewer degrees of freedom two
fewer
parameters in the specification of a
state than the collection of complex
numbers that would define a vector in
the abstract space two one is the phase
the overall phase and the the other is
the magnitude of it we'll come back to
that okay that uh that's taken us a long
way um You probably uh saturated but I'm
not so we're going to
continue I'm on a
high questions um probability also has
to be can't be negative it has to yeah
yeah that's right so these These are
always positive okay think times it's
complex conjugate is always
positive is the evolution postulate uh
is what is the what the evolution we
haven't yeah we we haven't gotten to
that yet how how things change with time
yeah no we're at the level now of where
we were in classical physics when we
just said the state of a system is just
a point in a uh among a set of things
that's about where we are that's how
that's how far we've gotten we've not
talked about how how things
change in particular how the states of
system systems change we'll come to that
can so uh back the beginning when we had
this example of um you know measuring
these cubits and you had um the
apparatus at an angle and you and you
got the cosine of theta right so we're
going do it okay what okay I guess my
question was that that we got we somehow
got the idea that cosine of theta is
going to be the average of your
measurements should it be cosine
squ
no I see why I see where you're going
but okay not
right can you say that last po posture
one more time so I can get when you
measure something you push it into the
state you are measuring
no when you measure something you get a
result the result is statistically uh
determined meaning to say that you may
get one result you may get another
result but once you get that
result then you know what state the
system is in it's in the igen
state of the quantity that you measured
with the igen value that came up on your
on your
detector
remember when we had our
apparatus and we measured Sigma Z we
said that not only measures Sigma Z but
It prepares the system in a state of
definite Sigma Z it leaves it over in a
state in which Sigma Z is definite for
the next measurement that means it
leaves it in an igen state of Sigma
Z
okay let's see if we can apply this
to to the spin
system
we get a very general
formulation and now we want to try it
out and see how it
works all right so the I want to start
with the three observables sigma X Sigma
Y and sigma Z and see what I can learn
about
them first of all Sigma
Z now let's
start in the basis
associated with the measurement of the
spin along the z-axis let's take that as
the appropriate
basis uh Sigma Z has two igen vectors by
from the experiments that we talked
about we would have learned have we done
the experiment that Sigma Z has two igen
values and two igen vectors the two igen
vectors we've called up and down and
they're associated with Sigma Z equals +
one and minus one those must be the igen
vectors of Sigma Z and igen values and
so we can immediately say Sigma Z times
up is equal to up+ one time
up why because the measured
value when we measure Sigma Z is going
to be +
one that's the igen value and up is the
igen vector because in the UP State
Sigma Z is definite what about Sigma Z
on the down
state what should I write
there is Sigma Z definite in the down
state yes it's always minus one it's
going to be minus one and that means the
igen value is minus
one time
down it's not Sigma Z * down equals up
that wouldn't be an igen Vector an igen
Vector has the property that when the
operator acts on it it gives the same
direction back times the igen value so
here is what we know
about Sigma
Z okay let's see if we can compute its
Matrix elements and exhibit it as a
matrix but when I say exhibited as a
matrix I have picked I must pick a
basis I'm going to pick the basis up and
down first of all One Thing Up and Down
are orthogonal to each other they must
be according to these principles because
if Sigma Z is an observable it
corresponds to a hermiss
matrix if there are two different igen
values the igen vectors must be
orthogonal for Herm Mission Matrix and
so up and down we first of all learn
that up and down are orthogonal that's
one
fact so it doesn't matter whether we
write up down or down up I mean we could
write it in the opposite order let's see
if if we can compute The Matrix elements
The Matrix elements are just the array
that we get when we consider the four
possibilities they're going to be 2 x
two
matrices and the four possibilities are
going to be first of all we take the
inner product of this back with up
that'll be the up up Matrix element or
the one one Matrix element what is that
going to
be uh to find let's I'm not sure I want
to uh
let's let's do it over
here let's calculate up Sigma Z up
that's equal Sigma Z acts to the right
to give us up + one well plus one is
just one times
up just the inner product of up with
itself and since up is a basis Vector
it's normalized and and this is just
equal to one its magnitude is equal to
one I can choose it to be equal to
one
uh it's positive yeah it's positive it's
real and it's just plain one so up here
in the up up or the one one place it's
just
one now let's what about the off
diagonal element the off diagonal
element that's that's an off diagonal
element there
that's going to be equal to the inner
product of downward
up what's
that zero over
here I would get exactly the same thing
if I put down over here and up over here
then I would use this equation over here
let Sigma Z act on down and then take
its overlap with up and I would get zero
again and the last one is down Sigma Z
down
what is that well you go over to here
Sigma Z * down is minus down so this is
just equal to minus down down and what's
that minus
one so this is the Matrix that's
associated with Sigma
Z when it acts on a vector on a column
Vector in particular when it acts what
is the column Vector that's associated
with up
it's just a one in the top and a zero in
the bottom all right so let's just try
this one
zero what do we get we get 1 * 1 is 1 0
* 0 0 we just get the same Vector back
that's good
okay same thing we'll get it's
guaranteed that we'll get the right that
the igen vectors are what they're
supposed to be namely just up and down
and that the igen values are plus one
and minus one in the right way all right
so we found one of the sigma matrices
Sigma
Z these are of course well not of course
they're called the POI matrices Sigma X
Sigma Y and sigma Z let's see what we
can find out about Sigma
X now I'm using if I use the X basis if
I use the basis of left and right of
course I would just find exactly the
same thing but I want to stick with the
up down basis I want to stick with the
up down basis but find out what the
Matrix elements of Sigma X
are now what is the property of Sigma X
the property of Sigma X is that its igen
vectors are left and right so for
example Sigma X on right that equals
right and what about Sigma X on
left
equals minus
left those are the two possible values
that Sigma X can take
on left and right are the igen vectors
in other words the states in which Sigma
X has definite values plus one and minus
one and this is what I know about Sigma
X but I want to find its Matrix elements
in the up down basis so what I really
want then let's uh let's come over to
here and see if we can compute in the
same basis what did I do with the the
poly Matrix did I erase
it I worked so hard to get
it Sigma Z is equal to 1 - 1 0
0 now we want to try to get Sigma X so
the first step is raise the black oh is
erase the erase the
Blackboard
and let's start one by one there are
four Matrix elements Let's uh do them
one by
one up Sigma X up now what we have to
know is that
up is equal to left plus
right over theare < TK of two you
remember
that we originally defined left and
right to be up plus or minus down over
the < TK of two but then we can solve
for up and down in terms of left and
right down down
is left uh sorry it's right minus
left with a notation we had last time it
was down no sorry it's
right minus left over <
tk2 so all we have to do is plug them
in on the left here we have left you
know I'm going to I'm going to abuse
notation and just write this as left
plus right over Square < TK of two this
is a meaningless
uh symbol but you I think you know what
I mean I mean the bra Vector left plus
the bra Vector right over the < TK of
two but uh too many vertical strokes and
I get confused so let's just write it as
left plus right over the > of two Sigma
X left plus right over squ < TK of
two first of all I can take out this is
the what is this thing this is Sigma X
up up there it is it's the up up
entry one that goes up in
here all right first of all there's a
factor of two that I can take out square
root of two from here and a squ > of two
from here that's alog together
1/2 and now let's look at this what
happens when Sigma X hits
left it gives back left except with a
minus
sign what happens when Sigma X hits
right it gives back right with a plus
sign so when Sigma X acts on this what
it winds up giving you can take the
sigma X away and just remember what it
does it gives right minus
left instead of right plus
left it hits the
vector right and gives plus one it hits
the vector left and gives minus one
again these are not things to be
numerically added these are vectors the
right Vector minus the left vector and
now what we have to do is take the inner
products well the inner product of right
with right right is
what one the inner product of right with
left is zero the inner product of left
with right is zero and the inner product
with left with
left minus one when you account for this
minus the result is they
cancel all right 1 minus one or
equivalently the in a
product of um of of a well okay zero Z
so first of all there's a zero over
here that's the up up Matrix
element it's easy to get the down down
Matrix element the down down Matrix
element you would do exactly the same
thing you except that you would start
with right minus Left Right minus
Left Right minus
left Sigma X and then you would say that
when Sigma X hits right it's plus right
when it hits left it gives minus left so
when Sigma X acts it takes right minus
left to right plus
left and what's the inner product of
right plus left with my right minus
left zero
again right with right is one left with
left is minus one and the cross terms
are just zero so there's a zero over
here now looks like all we're going to
get is zeros but that can't be right so
let's try
let's try up
down all right we try up down let's put
up down there up will be right plus left
we'll have Sigma
X and then down is Right minus
left what happens when Sigma X hits
right plus left it makes right minus
left and now what's the inner product
the inner product of right with right is
one the inner product of minus left with
minus left is also + one so they add and
again the cross terms between right and
left are zero so we get two / two which
is one get a one up
here and if we work it out we'll get
another one over
here all right so now we've got Sigma y
let's just stop for a minute and say
what is it that we have we have a pair
of linear operators or a pair of
matrices whose igen vectors
are this fellow's igen vectors here are
up and down this fellow's zigen vectors
are right and left they're exactly what
we were talking about on the previous
Blackboard
the states in which the observables have
unambiguous results are the igen
vectors so that's where we are now the
last one is Sigma y okay what do we know
about Sigma y I'm
Not In and Out are the igen vectors the
one we just did is Sigma X right when we
just Sigma X you Sig y you Sig y oh
Sigma X sorry thank
you actually don't think I wrote Sigma y
I think I just failed to cross the X I
think I don't know maybe I wrot Sigma
y all right the next one is Sigma Y and
here I'm going to leave some of the some
of the algeb this is very easy to you
but let's see what the uh what the rules
are oh in
incidentally uh no I think we're
okay we don't we we know the
rules okay so there was in and
out I cannot remember which one was
which uh so I'm going to fake it and if
it comes out wrong it comes out wrong
um I think
in was
up plus I think
itimes
down and out was
up minus I * down and I think I left out
factors of square < TK of
two
inally you can check that in and out are
orthogonal to each
other okay there there's in and out can
we find a
matrix
which in and out AR vectors with I value
plus one and minus one it's getting late
it's very easy leave it to you I will
simply tell you what that Matrix is it's
Unique it's Unique if you know the igen
vectors and you know the igen values
it's Unique one way of doing it is to
solve for up and down in terms of in
andout once you've solved for up and
down in terms of in and out and you know
how the Matrix acts on in and out you're
finished
the last one in the multiplet
here now I am writing Sigma
y similar to this
one but it's O minus I and
I all right so a little exercise you
don't really need to go and prove this
you can do a different thing you can
take this Matrix and show that these are
the igen vectors of
it you just show that these are the igen
vectors of it you take this Matrix and
show that it's igen vectors what is that
mean it means that it's IG vectors are 1
I and one minus I the square root of two
doesn't
matter igen vectors are igen vector they
don't care about the square root of
two these are the three poly
matrices that represent the components
of a spin in different
directions uh I think I think uh that's
enough for tonight what I was going to
do and I have in my notes was exactly
this question what happens if you have a
component of spin along an arbitrary
Direction can we show using what we know
that the pro we'll do this next time
we'll do this next time if we have a
component of spin along an arbitrary
Direction and we want to calculate using
the principles we want to calculate what
the probability
is for the measurement of Sigma Z in
various either plus or minus we should
be able to do it we have enough
information I think it's probably more
than uh than we can yet handle for
tonight think we did a lot for
tonight probably more than reason Am I
Wrong to use need to be negative to make
those two
work does one of the U's need to be
negative no no you know what you're
missing you're missing that you have to
complex
conjugate if you want the inner product
of in without you multiply 1 * 1 and
then add I not time minus I but I * plus
I yeah
yeah the only way that somebody like me
knows so quickly why what you're
thinking is having made the same mistake
of course
sometime in the
past
okay all right we'll finished for
tonight I think unless there's
questions for more please visit us at
stanford.edu